Art Collection, 1857-1988
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Art collection
1857-1988
1920-1980
MS 429
3 boxes; 2 volumes (1.25 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Documents women's participation in, and contributions to, the broad field of art. Contains primarily printed material, plus, correspondence, interviews, notes, photographs, postcards, posters, speeches, and typescripts. The collection documents the lives and work of individual designers, landscape architects, women in the fine arts, as well as the status of women in the arts and organizations of feminist artists.
The Art Collection documents women's participation in, and contributions to, the broad field of art from 1857 to 1988. The material consists of articles, autographs, bibliographies, brochures, catalogs, correspondence, interviews, newsletters, newspaper clippings, notes, pamphlets, photographs, postcards, posters, publicity, resumés, a reel-to-reel tape, speeches, and typescripts. There are only a few items dating from the nineteenth century, all of which are magazine articles or newspaper clippings that focus on the lives and work of individual women artists, including Angelica Kaufman and Rosa Bonheur. The bulk of the collection dates from the twentieth century, with most items originating between 1920 and 1980. The earlier twentieth century material documents women's contributions to the fields of visual art, architecture, landscape architecture, and graphic design. This includes biographical materials on designers Florence Morton and Helen Dryden; landscape architects Adelaide Derringer, Louise Klein-Miller, and Beatrix Farrand; and artists Mary Cassatt, Katharine S. Dreier, Caroline Durieux, Sarah Eddy Jackson, Beth Creevey, Hildreth Meiere, and Georgia O'Keeffe.
There is also a large amount of material in the collection dating from the late 1960s and 1970s documenting the impact of feminism on the art world, showing both the reassessment of women's historical contributions to the field, and the explosion of feminist art that occurred in the 1970s. Included here are studies and reports on the status of women in the arts, catalogs for exhibits of feminist art, newsletters from organizations of feminist artists, and material on contemporary women artists such as Judy Chicago, Alice Neel, Louise Grassie, Frieda Savitz, Myrna Shiras, Lilly Martin Spencer, and many others.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The collection is open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
Additions to the Collection
Periodic additions to collection are expected.
History of the Collection
Materials in this subject collection were either purchased or given to the Sophia Smith Collection by various donors.
Search Terms
Women artists--History--20th century--Sources; Women artists--History--19th century--Sources; Feminism and art--History--Sources; Women architects--History--Sources; Women designers-- History--Sources; Women landscape architects--History--Sources; Women motion picture producers and directors--History--Sources
- General
  - Guide to Women's Art Organizations (Box 1)
  - Art festivals and gallery shows (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bibliography: women and the arts (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Clippings (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The New Art Examiner (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - New York Feminist Art Institute (Box 1, Folder 5a)
  - Pamphlets (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Virginia Center for the Performing Arts (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - The Dinner Party by Judy Chicago (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Womanhouse, Los Angeles circa 1971 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Architects (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Designers (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Filmmakers: films (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Landscape architects
  - Farrand, Beatrix (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - General (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Painters
  - General bulletins (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Baker, Sarah (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Beaux, C.; Kauffman, A.; and Smith, Jessie Willcox (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Bonheur, Rose; and Brownscombe, Jennie (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Brooks, Romaine (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Brown, Gwyneth King (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Cassatt, Mary (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Dreier, Katherine S. (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Durieux, Caroline
    - Articles and programs (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Clippings (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Eddy, Sarah Jackson (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Grassie, Louise (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Hamm, Beth Creevey (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Harvey, Bunny (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Kollwitz, Kathe, 1867-1943 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Lumis, Harriet Randall (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Meiere, Hildreth (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Alice Neel: Presentation at Graham Hall, Smith College: audiotape, 8 Apr 1975 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    [Please use research copy in media center]
  - O'Keeffe, Georgia (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Pereira, Irene Rice (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Reyneau, Betsy (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Saar, Betye (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Sand, George: portraits of and by her (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Savitz, Frieda (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Shiras, Myrna (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Spencer, Lily Martin (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Miscellaneous paintings by various women artists (Box 2, Folder 42)
- Sculptors
  - General and miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Watertown's Victoria Legacy: A Bicentennial Art Exhibition (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Studio 725 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Bourgeois, Louise (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Chicago, Judy (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Dallin, Cyrus and Vittoria (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Hosmer, Harriet (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Huntington, Anna Hyatt (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Johnson, Adelaide
    - Letters to Una Winter (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Biographical information (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Loring, Francese (and Florence Wyle) (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Miles, Emily W. (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Nevelson, Louise (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Paeff, Bashka (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Stebbins, Emma (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Whitney, Anne (Box 3, Folder 58)
- Books on Shelf
  - Art and Handicraft in the Woman's Building of the World's Columbian Exposition Chicago, 1893, Elliot, Maud Howe, ed., 1894
  - True Colors: An Artist's Journey from Beauty Queen to Feminist by Patricia Burnett, 1995
  - Doin' It in Public: Feminism and Art at the Woman's Building (Exhibition guide and article), Megalinton and Sue Maberry, curator 2012
  - From Site to Vision: The Women's Building in Contemporary Culture, Sondra Hale and Terry Wolverton, editors 2012
  - DVD: Never Turning Back: The World of Peggy Lipschutz, Terri Zbinal, producer 2008